Previously on the show.
Episode sebelumnya.
Cloud Giant finally returned to the cloud sea tunnel.
Raksasa Awan telah kembali ke terowongan laut awan.
The giant, Slowy, Mechanical Bird and Wolffy
Raksasa, Slowy, Burung Mekanik dan Wolffy
told the tale of what happened.
menceritakan kisah yang sebenarnya terjadi.
Once the truth has been told,
Setelah kebenaran terungkap,
the Cloud Giant begins to put the sky crystal back together.
Raksasa Awan kembali menyatukan kristal langit.
Will things really go smoothly?
Apa semua akan berjalan lancar?
"Flying Island: The Sky Adventure: The Final Sky Crystal"
Petualangan Langit Pulau Terbang: Kristal Langit Yang Terakhir.
Let's begin then.
Ayo mulai.
Sky crystal fragment extraction!
Ekstraksi pecahan kristal langit!
Extract!
Ekstraksi!
We're still missing one fragment.
Masih kurang satu pecahan.
Why would we still miss one?
Kenapa bisa kurang satu?
Forget it.
Lupakan.
Based on my experience, when you lose something,
Berdasarkan pengalamanku, saat kehilangan sesuatu,
you never find it when you look for it.
takkan ketemu jika kau cari.
When you stop looking for it, it'll appear on its own.
Jika berhenti mencari, itu akan muncul dengan sendirinya.
So quit thinking about it.
Jadi, berhenti mencarinya.
Go back to your normal routine.
Kembali saja ke rutinitasmu.
That can't be true, Paddi. Get up and help us look for it.
Tak bisa begitu, Paddi. Bangun dan bantu kami mencarinya.
What is that?
Apa itu?
Is Paddi right after all?
Apakah Paddi benar?
No, this is just a marble.
Ini hanya kelereng.
Weslie, that marble is mine.
Weslie, itu kelerengku.
Willie? Why are you here?
Willie? Kenapa kau di sini?
Dad is too busy to play with me.
Ayah terlalu sibuk bermain denganku.
He told me to come play with you guys.
Dia menyuruhku bermain dengan kalian.
I'm sorry, Willie. We're too busy to play as well.
Maaf, Willie. Kami terlalu sibuk untuk bisa bermain.
What are you busy with?
Sibuk dengan apa?
We can't find the last missing sky crystal fragment.
Kami tak bisa temukan pecahan kristal langit yang terakhir.
I see. Can I borrow your remote control car then?
Begitu. Boleh kupinjam mobil pengendali jarak jauhmu?
Of course. Go get it from our Magic Train.
Tentu saja. Ambil dari Kereta Ajaib.
Thank you, Sparky.
Terima kasih, Sparky.
It's about time for Willie to get home.
Willie seharusnya sudah pulang.
I'm home, Dad!
Aku pulang, Ayah.
Are you tired, son?
Kau sudah lelah, Nak?
Yes! I'm a bit hungry too.
Ya! Aku juga agak lapar.
Your mom bought tasty snacks. Go and have some.
Ibumu beli camilan lezat. Pergi dan makanlah.
Okay!
Baik!
Willie, we're too busy to play as well.
Willie. Kami terlalu sibuk untuk bisa bermain.
We can't find the last missing sky crystal fragment.
Kami tak bisa temukan pecahan kristal langit yang terakhir.
They're missing a sky crystal fragment? Where could it be?
Ada pecahan kristal langit hilang? Kira-kira di mana?
Dad!
Ayah!
Son, why are you back?
Nak, kenapa kau kembali?
Have you seen the sensor joystick for the remote control car?
Ayah lihat joystick mobil mainan?
Just a moment. Here!
Tunggu sebentar. Ini!
Thanks, Dad!
- Terima kasih, Ayah! - Sama-sama!
Sensor joystick...
Sensor joystick...
I know!
Aku tahu!
Where could the last sky crystal fragment be?
Di mana pecahan kristal langit terakhir?
Come to think of it, Wolffy was there the day sky crystal shattered.
Kalau dipikir-pikir, ada Wolffy saat kristal langit hancur.
Yes, he must have the last fragment!
Ya, dia pasti punya pecahan terakhir!
That's slander! Pure slander! Blatant slander!
Itu fitnah! Fitnah murni! Jelas fitnah!
Wolffy? What do you want?
Wolffy? Apa maumu?
You keep making false accusations about me!
Kau terus buat tuduhan palsu tentangku!
You said I stole the colored pencil when you lost it.
Kau bilang aku mencuri pensil warna saat punyamu hilang.
Then you blamed me for stealing the star diamond.
Lalu kau menyalahkanku karena mencuri berlian bintang.
I'm a simple wolf.
Aku hanya serigala biasa.
All I want is to eat goats.
Aku hanya mau makan kambing.
Why do you keep falsely accusing me?
Kenapa kau terus menuduhku?
We searched him. There are no fragments.
Dia sudah digeledah. Tak ada pecahan.
He doesn't have a mark on his hand either.
Tak ada tanda di tangannya juga.
Seems like Wolffy really doesn't have the sky crystal.
Sepertinya Wolffy memang tak punya kristal langit.
Huh, do you believe I'm innocent now?
Apa kau percaya aku tak bersalah sekarang?
Right, Wolffy, why are you here?
Wolffy, kenapa kau di sini?
It's a long story.
Ceritanya panjang.
The thing is,
Masalahnya,
the precious gemstone I bought Wolnie, the desert tear, has gone missing.
batu permata yang kubeli untuk Wolnie, air mata gurun, hilang.
It might be mixed with Willie's marbles.
Mungkin tercampur dengan kelereng Willie.
So I'm wondering if it could be with you.
Jadi, aku mau tahu apa kalian memilikinya.
Could Willie have left it on Magic Train when he was playing there?
Apa Willie meninggalkannya di Kereta Ajaib saat dia bermain di sana?
Can I go look for the gem inside Magic Train?
Aku boleh mencari permatanya di dalam Kereta Ajaib?
Why don't we let Wolffy in for a look?
Kenapa kita tak biarkan Wolffy mencari?
No! He must be plotting something.
Tidak! Dia pasti sedang bersiasat!
It's fine. The other sky crystal fragments are with Cloud Giant.
Tak apa. Pecahan kristal langit lain di Raksasa Awan.
Magic Train isn't functioning right now.
Kereta Ajaib sedang tak menyala.
Go on then, since Village Chief agreed.
Masuklah, karena Kepala Desa setuju.
Thank you so much.
Terima kasih banyak.
Hold on!
Tunggu!
Don't eat my biscuits!
Jangan makan kukisku!
Of course...
Tentu saja...
Everyone,
Semuanya...
Cloud Giant wants to ask you how you found sky crystal.
Raksasa Awan mau bertanya bagaimana kau menemukan kristal langit.
Cloud Giant wants to see us?
Raksasa awan mau bertemu?
He may have come up with clues on sky crystal. Let's go then.
Dia mungkin menemukan petunjuk soal kristal langit. Ayo pergi.
I'm worried about Wolffy's intentions.
Aku cemas soal ketulusan Wolffy.
Why don't you keep an eye on Wolffy, Paddi?
Kau bisa awasi Wolffy, Paddi?
Yes, since you're so worried that he would eat your biscuits.
Karena kau cemas kukismu akan dia makan.
Why me?
Kenapa aku?
It's fine. We'll be back soon.
Tak apa. Kami segera kembali.
I'm starving.
Aku lapar.
Older brother, the chips we got at the mall were so good.
Kakak, keripik yang kita makan di mal sangat enak.
Remember to buy more next time.
- Nanti harus beli lagi. - Baiklah.
Snacks? I know what to do!
Camilan? Aku tahu!
If I guessed right, it must be inside Magic Train.
Jika tebakanku benar, itu pasti di dalam Kereta Ajaib.
Wolffy! I'm watching you! Don't try anything funny!
Wolffy! Aku mengawasimu! Jangan coba berbuat aneh!
Since when did Paddi get so serious?
Sejak kapan Paddi jadi serius?
This isn't like him.
Ini tak seperti dia.
Wolffy, I'm watching you!
Wolffy! Aku mengawasimu!
So delicious!
Lezat sekali.
I am sorry if you feel like I'm showing off.
Maaf jika kau merasa aku pamer.
It's all my Wolffy's fault. He insisted on buying me this huge, expensive gem.
Ini gara-gara Wolffy. Dia bersikeras membelikanku permata besar ini.
He said it's called desert tear.
Dia bilang ini disebut air mata gurun.
Desert tear? Didn't Wolffy say it was lost? Was he...
Air mata gurun? Kata Wolffy bilang itu hilang? Apa dia...
I have some clues.
Aku punya petunjuk.
Could you tell me how you found your missing friends?
Bisa ceritakan caramu menemukan teman-temanmu yang hilang?
The radar on Magic Train can detect them.
Radar di Kereta Ajaib bisa mendeteksi mereka.
Based on what I know, only sky crystals can resonate with and detect each other.
Setahuku, hanya kristal langit yang bisa beresonansi dan saling mendeteksi.
No wonder the radar started detecting the locations of my other friends
Pantas radar mulai mendeteksi lokasi temanku yang lain
after using sky crystal for the first time in Tower Town.
saat pertama memakai kristal langit di Kota Menara.
So the last sky crystal fragment may very well be in Magic Train.
Jadi, pecahan kristal langit terakhir mungkin ada di Kereta Ajaib.
Oh, no!
Tidak!
Paddi, weren't you supposed to be watching Wolffy?
Paddi, bukankah seharusnya kau mengawasi Wolffy?
I saw with my own eyes that the gem is still with Wolnie!
Aku lihat sendiri bahwa permata itu bersama Wolnie!
What?
Apa?
So Wolffy went on Magic Train to find the missing sky crystal fragment.
Wolffy pergi ke Kereta Ajaib untuk mencari pecahan kristal langit yang hilang.
Where is it? Why can't I find it?
Di mana? Mengapa tak kutemukan?
Wolffy, you really are up to no good!
Wolffy, kau benar-benar jahat!
How did they find out so quickly?
Kenapa mereka bisa cepat tahu?
Wolffy, we have you surrounded. Hand over the energy extractor now.
Wolffy, kau sudah terkepung. Serahkan ekstraktor energi sekarang.
Come get it, if you dare!
Ambil saja kalau berani!
A camera?
Kamera?
How despicable of you, Wolffy!
Kau licik sekali, Wolffy!
How could you tap Magic Train to spy on us?
Kau tega menyadap Kereta Ajaib untuk memata-matai kami?
Will you stop making false accusations about me?
Bisakah kau berhenti membuat tuduhan palsu tentangku?
As a high-end inventor, if I were to spy on you,
Sebagai penemu hebat, jika aku memata-mataimu,
would I use such cheap and outdated equipment?
apa aku akan pakai peralatan murah dan kuno?
If I were to spy on you, I would be using this!
Jika memata-mataimu, aku akan memakai ini!
Oh! Isn't that Willie's cap?
Bukankah itu topi Willie?
I can't believe you used Willie to spy on us.
Aku tak percaya kau memanfaatkan Willie untuk memata-matai kami.
You're terrible!
Kau jahat!
But if this isn't Wolffy's,
Jika ini bukan punya Wolffy,
who is spying on us then?
siapa yang memata-matai kita?
Don't think of running, Wolffy!
Jangan coba lari, Wolffy!
Sky crystal...
Kristal langit...
I'm right, after all. Sky crystal is on Magic Train!
Aku benar. Kristal langit ada di Kereta Ajaib!
Wolffy, you won't get away this time! Hand over sky crystal now!
Wolffy, kali ini kau takkan lolos! Serahkan kristal langit!
Since I decided to come, I came prepared.
Karena aku memutuskan untuk kemari, aku sudah siap.
Be careful, everyone!
Hati-hati, Semua!
Goodbye, goats!
Selamat tinggal, Kambing!
Stop escaping!
Berhenti kabur!
Escape? You are always the ones escaping from me!
Kabur? Kalian yang selalu kabur dariku!
Dance, Wolffy!
Menari, Wolffy!
I forgot we don't have sky crystals anymore!
Aku lupa kita tak punya kristal langit!
Magic Train is garbage without sky crystal!
Kereta Ajaib tak berguna tanpa kristal langit!
Get a taste of my Sirius missile!
Rasakan rudal Sirius-ku!
I'll see how long you can dodge this!
Akan kulihat berapa lama kau bisa menghindar!
Don't hurt the goats, Wolffy!
Jangan sakiti kambing, Wolffy!
You're also here, Cloud Giant?
Kau juga di sini, Raksasa Awan?
Wolffy, you can't escape this time!
Wolffy, kini kau tak bisa kabur!
I'll admit defeat, all right?
Aku akan mengaku kalah, ya?
You can have sky crystal. Go look for it!
Ambil kristal langitnya. Cari sana.
Wolffy, you--
Wolffy, kau...
I have sky crystal!
Aku punya kristal langit!
It's a marble! Wolffy fooled us!
Itu kelereng! Wolffy menipu kita!
Sky crystal is mine now!
Kristal langit menjadi milikku!
Oh, no. We are too late.
Gawat. Kita terlambat.
Perfect timing.
Waktu yang tepat.
Let me show you the true power of sky crystal!
Biar kutunjukkan kekuatan sejati kristal langit!
TO BE CONTINUED
BERSAMBUNG